Register of the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions Records, 1961-1968
Wisconsin Historical Society
International Confederation of Free Trade Unions Records, 1961-1968
International Confederation of Free Trade Unions
Mss 519
2.4 c.f. (6 archives boxes)
Wisconsin Historical Society, Library-Archives Division
Records of the New York office of an international association of labor unions. The organization, formed in 1949, is concerned with the influence of communist unions in economically underdeveloped nations in Africa, Asia, and Latin America, and has consultative status to the United Nations and its specialized agencies. The records reflect the New York office's activities of informing and influencing the United Nations on worldwide issues such as racism, unionism, workers' rights, economic development, and trade. The materials in the collection include correspondence, telegrams, reports, texts of statements, United Nations documents, and newspaper clippings.
The International Confederation of Free Trade Unions (ICFTU) was formed in 1949 by trade union federations that had withdrawn from the World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU) after disagreements with communist unions. The principal unions organizing ICFTU were the British Transport and General Workers Union, the British Trade Union Congress, the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO), and the American Federation of Labor (AFL). The first congress of ICFTU was held in London in early December of 1949. At its foundation the organization had nearly 48 million members from 70 labor organizations in 53 countries or territories. By 1964 its membership had increased to nearly 60 million members in 120 affiliated organizations in 94 countries or territories.
The objectives in forming ICFTU were to unite workers organized in the non-communist and democratic trade unions of the world, and to afford a means of consultation and collaboration between them. The organization's activities are concerned officially with upholding universal values of human dignity; political and economic democracy and social justice through peace, freedom, self-determination and national independence; trade union rights; and economic and social progress. To promote democratic unionism in economically undeveloped countries in Africa, Asia, and Latin America, ICFTU has established vocational training centers and cooperatives for both health care and low cost housing.
To effectively fulfill the purposes and objectives of ICFTU, regional organizations were set up in Asia, Latin America, Europe, and later in Africa. The Asian Regional Organization (ICTFU-ARO), with headquarters in New Delhi, was developed in 1951. Also in that year the Latin American Association -- Organizacion Regional Interamerica de Trabajadores (ORIT) -- was established in Mexico City. The European Regional Organization (ICTFU-ERO) began in 1957.
Soon after ICTFU was formed in 1949, it obtained consultative status to the United Nations and the UN's specialized agencies. The various agencies to which the union makes suggestions and conducts observations include the Economic and Social Council (ECOSOC); the Regional Economic Commissions for Africa, Asia, Europe, and Latin America; the Trade and Development Board; the Commissions on Human Rights and on the Status of Women; the International Labor Organization (ILO); and the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO). To facilitate communication with the agencies of the United Nations, ICFTU offices were established in New York, Paris, and Geneva.
The major periodical publications of ICFTU are Free Labor World, Economic and Social Bulletin, and International Trade Union News.
Although the collection consists of the records of the New York Office from 1961 to 1968, the records are far more comprehensive for the period after the office was reorganized in 1962. The materials include correspondence, telegrams, reports, texts of statements, and newspaper clippings. Since the correspondence is arranged both by individuals and by subjects, there is some duplication of correspondence. In addition, while the majority of the material is in English, the international scope of the organization is reflected by records in Spanish, French, and German.
The ORGANIZATIONAL RECORDS OF THE NEW YORK OFFICE document the internal operation of the office. Although some correspondence for 1961 is contained in scattered files throughout the collection, the majority of information for that year is included in the outgoing correspondence of Bill Kemsley and Marvin Schlaff. The staff activities related to the United Nations and other organizations are reflected in the miscellaneous correspondence. There are also a few reports on activities for 1963-1964, correspondence and reports on the activities of individuals visiting the office, staff procedures for handling such things as telephone messages and correspondence, and miscellaneous correspondence not included in the various subject files.
The series CORRESPONDENCE comprises over a quarter of the collection. Also included here are statements on issues and activity reports. Among the correspondents are individuals associated with ICFTU, including New York office personnel, personnel of the Brussels headquarters, personnel of ICFTU regional organizations, and ICFTU consultants. These records cover a wide range of topics including routine business; activities related to Africa, Asia, and Latin America; and activities related to the United Nations and its various agencies. The emphasis of the informational records is concentrated on trade unions, development of trade, and economic development in Third World nations.
Included in the series UNITED NATIONS are letters, statements, memos, reports, and United Nations documents. Besides records created to inform and influence the General Assembly, the Economic and Social Council, and various missions to the General Assembly, the documents illustrate activities directed toward United Nations' sponsored commissions, organizations, and appeals for human rights and international cooperation. Also documented here is ICFTU's involvement in the United Nations Conference on Trade and Development, from December 1962 through November 1967. Records concerning the conference include correspondence, reports, and statements relating to trade unions, trade questions, rights of workers, and economic development.
Within the series OTHER ICFTU ACTIVITIES OF THE NEW YORK OFFICE can be found correspondence, reports, press releases, and resolutions about vocational training, cooperatives, and the status of women and youth. Also in this series is information on the seventh and eighth world congresses of ICFTU.
The last two series in the collection are RECORDS RELATING TO VARIOUS COUNTRIES and RECORDS RELATING TO VARIOUS ORGANIZATIONS. Documented in these series are interests and concerns of ICFTU relating to such topics as human rights, rights of workers, political prisoners, unions, colonialism, and racial discrimination. These materials include correspondence, press releases, reports, resolutions, and statements on union activities around the world. Here are also newspaper clippings from 1962-1965 on some of the conflicts between ICFTU and one of its chief sponsors, the AFL-CIO.
Administrative/Restriction Information
Presented by the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, New York, 1974. M74-185
- Organizational Records of the New York Office
  - Activity Reports, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Staff Procedures, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Visitors, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Correspondence
  - New York Office Personnel
    - Aguirre, Jose, 1965-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Baah, Kwaku, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Barton, Paul, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
    - Beichman, Arnold, 1962-1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Brown, Irving, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Cadet, Dorothy, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Brussels Headquarters Personnel
    - Barry-Braunthal, Tom, 1964-1967 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Becu, Omar. 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Braunthal, Alfred, 1961-1967 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - Paladino, Morris, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Pateet, Herman, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Riddle, John, 1961-1967 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Tulatz, Herbert, 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Regional Personnel and Organizations
    - African Regional Organization (ICFTU-AFRO), 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Asian Regional Organization (ICFTU-ARO), 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Gonzalez-Hermosilla, Basilio, 1964-1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Gonzalez-Tellechea, Ignacio, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Jaurequi, Arthura, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Organizacion Regional Interamerica de Trabajadores (ORIT), 1961-1967 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Valdivio, Raul, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Vazquez, Rolando Lopez, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - ICFTU Consultants
    - Bernaut, Roman, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Collinet, Michael, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Ford, Charles, 1965-1968 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Gorkin, Julian, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Klatt, Werner, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - White, Lawrence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- United Nations
  - General Assembly, 1962-1967 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Economic and Social Council (ECOSOC), 1962-1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Trade Union Representation in the United Nations, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - ICFTU Representation in the United Nations, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Missions to the United Nations
    - United States, 1961-1966 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - United Kingdom, 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Other Countries, 1961-1965 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Economic Commission for Africa (ECA), 1963-1965 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Economic Commission for Latin America (ECLA), 1962-1965 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO), 1966 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Human Rights, 1962-1967 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - International Cooperation Year, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - International Labor Organization (ILO), 1963-1966 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Organization for Industrial Development, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - United Nations Conference on Trade and Development
    - Conference on Trade and Development (UNCAD)
      - 1962-1964, February (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
      - 1964, March - 1967 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
    - ICFTU Committee on International Trade Questions, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - ICFTU Subcommittee on the United Nations Conference on Trade and Development, 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
- Other ICFTU Activities of the New York Office
  - Vocational Training, 1963-1967 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Women and Youth Department, 1961-1967 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Working Group on Cooperatives, Vocational Training, and Other Forms of Economic and Social Action, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - World Youth Rally, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - World Congresses of ICFTU
    - Seventh Congress, 1962 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Eighth Congress, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - ICFTU Resolutions, 1963-1966 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Records Relating to Various Countries
  - Argentina, 1963-1967 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Australia, 1962-1965 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Barbados, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Burandi, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Ceylon, 1962-1965 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Costa Rica, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Cuba, 1962-1965 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Cyprus, 1962-1965 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Germany, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Great Britain, 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - India, 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Italy, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Japan, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Malaysia, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Pakistan, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Rhodesia, 1965-1966 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - South Africa, 1963-1966 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Spain, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Sweden, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Trinidad and Tobago, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Tunisia, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Venezuela, 1962-1967 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Vietnam, 1962-1966 (Box 5, Folder 24)
- Records Relating to Other Organizations
  - Associated and Sponsored Organizations
    - African-American Labor Center, 1962-1967 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - African Labor College, 1965-1967 (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - African Research Office of ICFTU, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - AFL-CIO
      - Correspondence, 1962-1967 (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Newspaper Clippings, 1962-1965 (Box 6, Folder 2)
      - AFL-CIO Affiliates, 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Confederation Generale du Travail - Force Ouviere (CGT-FO), 1962-1967 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Miners International Federation (IMF), 1965-1966 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Postal, Telegraph and Telephone International (PTTI), 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Public Services International (PSI), 1962-1967 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Organizations Seeking ICFTU Support
    - American Negro Leadership Conference on Africa, 1966-1967 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - American Institute for Free Labor Development, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Amnesty International, 1965-1967 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Citizens Committee for a Free Cuba, 1963-1966 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Council Against Communist Aggression, 1966 (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Federation of Former Hungarian Political Prisoners, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Foreign Services of the United States of America, 1963-1966 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Frente Obrero Revolucionario Democratico Cubano (FORDC), 1963-1966 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - International Bank for Reconstruction and Development, 1962-1966 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - International Council of Voluntary Agencies, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - International Rescue Committee, 1962-1966 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - International Society for Rehabilitation of the Disabled, 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - International Transport Workers Federation (ITF), 1964-1967 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Various Jewish Organizations, 1963-1966 (Box 6, Folder 21)
Appendix: Individuals Associated with ICFTU
Aguirre, Jose
Specialist on Latin America in the New York Office
Baah, Kwaku
New York Staff member primarily concerned with Africa.
Barry-Braunthal, Tom
ICFTU press officer in Brussels
Barton, Paul
Primarily concerned with economic and social affairs, New York office and in Switzerland
Becu, Omer
General secretary of ICFTU in Brussels
Beichman, Arnold
Press representative of the New York office
Bernaut, Roman
French trade union specialist considered for a New York Office position
Braunthal, Alfred
Assistant General Secretary of ICFTU in Brussels
Brown, Irving
Director of the New York Office
Cadet, Dorothy
Administrative Assistant of the New York Office
Collinet, Michael
Consultant to ICFTU on the United Nations Economic and Social Council (ECOSOC)
Ford, Charles
Trade Union Advisory Committee
Gonzalez-Hermosilla, Basilio
ORIT representative in Chile
Gonzalez-Tellechea, Ignacio
ORIT representative in New York
Gorkin, Julian
Director of the Centro de Documentacion y de Estudios, Paris
Jaurequi, Arthura
Secretary-General of ORIT in Mexico
Klatt, Werner
Consultant to ICFTU on the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO)
Paladino, Morris
Assistant General Secretary of ICFTU in Brussels
Patteet, Herman
Head of the Administration Department of ICFTU in Brussels
Riddle, John
Editor of Free Labour World
Tulatz, Herbert
Assistant General Secretary of ICFTU in Brussels
Valdivio, Raul
Assistant to the General Secretary of ORIT
Vazquez, Rolando Lopez
Director of ORIT's Departamento de Asuntos Economicos y Sociales, Mexico
White, Lawrence
Consultant to ICFTU on the International Labor Organization (ILO) and on trade and development